<!--
  Copyright 2012 The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
   All Rights Reserved.
  
   Permission to use, copy, modify OR distribute this software and its
   documentation for educational, research and non-profit purposes, without
   fee, and without a written agreement is hereby granted, provided that the
   above copyright notice and the following three paragraphs appear in all
   copies.
  
   IN NO EVENT SHALL THE UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL BE
   LIABLE TO ANY PARTY FOR DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR
   CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, INCLUDING LOST PROFITS, ARISING OUT OF THE
   USE OF THIS SOFTWARE AND ITS DOCUMENTATION, EVEN IF THE UNIVERSITY
   OF NORTH CAROLINA HAVE BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH
   DAMAGES.
  
   THE UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA SPECIFICALLY DISCLAIM ANY
   WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
   MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  THE SOFTWARE
   PROVIDED HEREUNDER IS ON AN "AS IS" BASIS, AND THE UNIVERSITY OF
   NORTH CAROLINA HAS NO OBLIGATIONS TO PROVIDE MAINTENANCE, SUPPORT,
   UPDATES, ENHANCEMENTS, OR MODIFICATIONS.
  
   The authors may be contacted via:
  
   US Mail:           Dennis Goldfarb
                      Wei Wang
  
                      Department of Computer Science
                        Sitterson Hall, CB #3175
                        University of N. Carolina
                        Chapel Hill, NC 27599-3175
  
                      Ben Major
  
                      Department of Cell Biology and Physiology 
                        Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center
                        University of N. Carolina
                        Chapel Hill, NC 27599-3175
  
   Email:             dennisg@cs.unc.edu
                      weiwang@cs.unc.edu
                      ben_major@med.unc.edu
  
   Web:               www.unc.edu/~dennisg/
-->
<!DOCTYPE ui:UiBinder SYSTEM "http://dl.google.com/gwt/DTD/xhtml.ent">
<ui:UiBinder xmlns:ui="urn:ui:com.google.gwt.uibinder"
				xmlns:g="urn:import:com.google.gwt.user.client.ui">
				
	<g:HTMLPanel>
		<div>
			<div id="uploadPanel"> 
				<p>A detailed description of Spotlite can be found in our paper:<br/>
					<a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/pr5008416" target="_blank">
						Spotlite: Web Application and Augmented Algorithms for Predicting Co-Complexed Proteins 
						from Affinity Purification - Mass Spectrometry Data.
					</a>
				</p>
				<h2>Upload Instructions</h2>
				<h3>Input File Format</h3>
				<p>The input to Spotlite is a tab-delimited file containing five columns. A header is optional. If a header is present it must
				match the example below.
				We recommend stringent cutoffs for protein identifications, such as a 1% FDR. For best results, experiments 
				should use the same purification technique, protocols, and mass spectrometer. The format of the file is as follows:</p>
				<table class="t1">
					<tbody>
						<tr>
							<td>Experiment ID</td>
							<td>Experiment Type</td>
							<td>Bait</td>
							<td>Prey</td>
							<td>Spectral Count</td>
						</tr>
					</tbody>
				</table>
				<div align="left">
					<p><b>Experiment IDs</b> can be any combination of numbers or letters. Each experiment must have a unique ID.</p>
					<p><b>Experiment Type</b> must be one of the following: T, or C. T=Test and C=Control</p>
					<p><b>Bait</b> and <b>Prey</b> must be either an Entrez Gene ID, IPI or UniProt Accession, or a Gene Symbol.
						Other identifiers are allowed, but will not be mapped to an Entrez Gene ID and therefore Spotlite will only
						use APMS data for scoring that interaction. For control experiments, the <b>Bait</b> identifier can be anything.</p>
					<p><b>Spectral Count</b> is an integer representing the total number of spectra for the corresponding prey.</p>
				</div>
				<h3>Example</h3>
					<table class="t1">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<th>Experiment ID</th><th>Experiment Type</th><th>Bait</th><th>Prey</th><th>Spectral Count</th>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>EXP_1</td><td>T</td><td>KEAP1</td><td>KEAP1</td><td>200</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>EXP_1</td><td>T</td><td>KEAP1</td><td>Q16236</td><td>5</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>EXP_2</td><td>T</td><td>CTNNB1</td><td>CTNNB1</td><td>100</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>EXP_2</td><td>T</td><td>CTNNB1</td><td>9817</td><td>17</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Control_1</td><td>C</td><td>EmptyVector</td><td>KRT17</td><td>44</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
				
				<h2>APMS Algorithm Choices</h2>
				<h3>CompPASS WD-score</h3>
					<p>A thorough description of the CompPASS WD-score is located <a href="http://falcon.hms.harvard.edu/ipmsmsdbs/cgi-bin/tutorial.cgi" target="_blank">here</a>. The WD-score's classification performance is hampered by very densely connected datasets as it is reliant on the uniqueness of prey.</p>
				<h3>HSCore</h3>
					<p>HGSCore is defined in in <a href="http://www.cell.com/abstract/S0092-8674(11)01080-4" target="_blank">this publication</a>. Its classification performance is best on large datasets where bait and prey are often tested in both directions.</p>
				<h3>SAINT</h3>
					<p>Spotlite uses <a href="http://saint-apms.sourceforge.net/Main.html" target="_blank">SAINTexpress</a> (version 3.1.0) because its fast computational speed is necessary for calculating p-values via permutations. SAINTexpress requires at least two control experiments and is the best method for datasets containing few baits.</p>
					
				<h2>Permutations</h2>
					<p>Permutations of the APMS dataset are performed to calculated p-values. 
					For HGSCore, permutations are continued until the number of permuted interactions is equal to 200x 
					the number of unique interactions of the original dataset. For SAINT and CompPASS - whose score 
					distribution is conditional on the number of replicates - permutations are continued until each replicate group
					has 200x the number of unique interactions. This can lead to long runtimes if, for example, a dataset contains 100 baits 
					with two replicates each and 1 bait with 1 replicate, because each dataset permutation will generate very few 
					interactions with 1 replicate.</p>
					
				<h2>Spotlite Column Descriptions</h2>
				<div align="left">
					<table class="t1">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<th>Column Name</th>
								<th>Column Description</th>
								<th>Database Minimum</th>
								<th>Database Maximum</th>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Classifier Score</td>
								<td>Probability of interaction based on our Spotlite logistic regression classifier.</td>
								<td></td>
								<td></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>APMS Score</td>
								<td>APMS score calculated using your chosen algorithm.</td>
								<td></td>
								<td></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>APMS Pvalue</td>
								<td>P-value calculated for the APMS score. The p-value is conditional on the number of replicates when using CompPASS or SAINT.</td>
								<td></td>
								<td></td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>BP</td>
								<td>Semantic similarity for GO Biological Process annotations.</td>
								<td>0.12814</td>
								<td>1.9989</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>CC</td>
								<td>Semantic similarity for GO Cellular Component annotations.</td>
								<td>0.073278</td>
								<td>1.9989</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>CXP Hsa</td>
								<td>Pearson's correlation coefficient (PCC) for human co-expression patterns.</td>
								<td>-0.389</td>
								<td>0.9698</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>CXP Mmu</td>
								<td>PCC for the highest co-expression patterns among a protein pair's mouse homologs.</td>
								<td>-0.3597</td>
								<td>0.9415</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>CXP Cel</td>
								<td>PCC for the highest co-expression patterns among a protein pair's C. elegans homologs.</td>
								<td>-0.6232</td>
								<td>0.9356</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>CXP Gga</td>
								<td>PCC for the highest co-expression patterns among a protein pair's chicken homologs.</td>
								<td>-0.7407</td>
								<td>0.9771</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>CXP Rno</td>
								<td>PCC for the highest co-expression patterns among a protein pair's rat homologs.</td>
								<td>-0.8839</td>
								<td>0.9267</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>CXP Dre</td>
								<td>PCC for the highest co-expression patterns among a protein pair's zebrafish homologs.</td>
								<td>-0.6203</td>
								<td>0.9629</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>CXP Mcc</td>
								<td>PCC for the highest co-expression patterns among a protein pair's rhesus macaque monkey homologs.</td>
								<td>-0.7918</td>
								<td>0.959</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Domain</td>
								<td>Probability of the protein pairs interacting determined by the probability of any of their domains interacting.</td>
								<td>0.000215</td>
								<td>0.3392</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Homo int</td>
								<td>Number of homolog pairs previously annotated to form a complex with each other.</td>
								<td>0.000567</td>
								<td>1.0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Hsa phen</td>
								<td>Semantic similarity for the Human Phenotype Ontology. <b>Not part of classifier: annotation only.</b></td>
								<td>0.16651</td>
								<td>0.19989</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Mmu phen</td>
								<td>Semantic similarity for the Mammalian Phenotype Ontology - mouse mutant phenotypes. <b>Not part of classifier: annotation only.</b></td>
								<td>0.16639</td>
								<td>0.19989</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Disease</td>
								<td>Semantic similarity for the Disease Ontology - human disease. <b>Not part of classifier: annotation only.</b></td>
								<td>0.047714</td>
								<td>0.19989</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Known</td>
								<td>Previously known interactions from BioGRID are annotated with "L" for low-throughput experiments and "H" for high-throughput. <b>Not part of classifier: annotation only.</b></td>
								<td></td>
								<td></td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>						
				</div>
				<h2>Database Version</h2>
					<p>Gene information, protein sequences, ontologies, domains, and protein-protein interactions were last updated on <b>10/05/13</b>.</p>
				<h2>False Discovery Rate</h2>
				<p>We use the Benjamini-Hochberg method to compute false discovery rates (FDR) for data based on APMS scores only. FDRs for Spotlite classifier results will be available in the future.</p> 
				<p>First, APMS score p-values are sorted in increasing order denoted by \(P_{ 1 },...,P_{n}\).</p>
				<p>Next, for a particular desired FDR, \(\alpha\), we find the largest \(k\) such that \(P_{k} \le \frac{k}{m}\alpha\), where \(m\) is the number of unique interactions in the dataset.</p>
				<!--  <p>\(P(k) = 1 - \frac{\sum_{i=1}^{i=x}P_{i}}{x}\) for \(x \in 1,2,...,n\).</p>-->
				<p>From the My Data page, the click "False Discovery Rate" and choose your desired FDR threshold.</p>
				<h2>Method Description</h2>
					<p>Spotlite uses a two-layer logistic regression model to predict protein-protein interactions from APMS data. Details can be found in Spotlite's publication.</p>
				<h2>Data Destruction</h2>
					<p>Datasets are automatically deleted after 24 hrs or manually by the user on "My Data" page.</p>
				<div align="left">
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
	</g:HTMLPanel>

</ui:UiBinder>
